Well, it's the end of unit 5, and I sure
wish I could tell you that
reconstruction in the United States
ended like a fairy tale with the North
and South holding hands and walking into
the sunset. But here's where I tell you
that it ended more like a Greekstinking
tragedy. And so, it's time to talk about
it. If you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay, so
before we get to all the tragic
failures, let's start by acknowledging
that during reconstruction, black
Americans did have some successes,
especially early on. And the soil out of
which those successes grew was a battle
royale between Congress and President
Andrew Johnson over who would control
reconstruction policies. Now, remember
from the last video that Andrew Johnson
became president because Lincoln got
himself assassinated shortly after he
was elected to a second term. And that
was a real problem because reuniting the
North and South after the war would
require no small amount of shrewd wisdom
and political imagination and diplomatic
skill. And if we compare reconstruction
to a symphony, then Lincoln showed up to
the task with an expertly crafted,
delicate, yet powerful Stratavarius
whose sounds could soar and bring the
whole orchestra into tune. [music] But
Johnson possessed none of Lincoln's
skill and showed up to the performance
with a cowbell, thinking that if he just
beat it hard enough, the beautiful music
of reunion would pour forth and Congress
would fall on their faces and proclaim,
"I got a fever and the only prescription
is more cowbell." The point is Johnson
was not nearly as equipped as Lincoln,
either in skill or temperament to bind
the deep wounds of the nation.
Regardless, let me talk about some of
the successes gained during the early
reconstruction years, and then I'll come
back to Johnson and show you how he
tried his absolute best to undo that
progress. Okay, so the first success was
the establishment of the Freriedman's
Bureau in 1865. It was essentially a
welfare agency tasked with assisting
both poor whites and freed blacks in the
South after the war. To that end, the
bureau provided food and shelter to
those who needed it and in the beginning
granted free people land that had
formerly been the possession of white
planters. And the land distribution is
going to be a big issue of contention,
but I'll tell you more about that later.
Additionally, the bureau established
thousands of schools for black children
and a handful of universities for black
adults. For example, in 1867, the first
all black college in the south was
established, namely Shaw University,
whose land was purchased with a
combination of private funds and money
from the Freriedman's Bureau. Okay. Now,
the second success in the early years of
reconstruction was the rise of black
Americans entering political office. So,
over the course of the reconstruction
years, more than 2,000 black men were
elected to political office, mostly in
local offices and state legislatores,
but also a handful were elected to the
House of Representatives and the Senate.
And much of the political participation
of black Americans was facilitated by
groups like the Union League. It was an
organization that had been formed during
the war in order to support Lincoln's
second election and help facilitate
Union policies. But after the war, they
opened many chapters throughout the
South and helped black men register to
vote and educated them to make sure that
they would vote Republican. And there
are other examples of successes that I
could give you, but now we need to
return to President Johnson and his
fantastic attempts to squash these
successes. Now, Johnson himself was a
southerner and an enslaver, and he had
very little desire to fundamentally
reshape southern society into a place in
which blacks and whites were equal. And
so, he made every effort he could to
veto congressional legislation that
supported black Americans, like for
example, the Civil Rights Act of 1866.
Johnson argued that imposing federal
laws to protect racial equality violated
states rights and that the South could
really figure itself out with respect to
the whole race thing. But in 1867,
radical Republicans gained a super
majority in Congress and they used that
power to take control of reconstruction
away from Johnson and into their own
hands. And as I mentioned in the last
video, one of the most consequential
decisions they made was to pass over
Johnson's veto the Military
Reconstruction Act, which divided the
South into five military districts and
staff them with US troops to ensure that
racial equality laws were being upheld.
And they also passed the enforcement
acts during the presidency of Ulissiz
Srant which allowed the federal
government to ensure that southern
states were not marginalizing black
voters. And they passed other similar
laws as well like the civil rights act
of 1875. All of which demonstrate that
the radical Republicans in Congress
meant to control the process of
reconstruction. Okay, so now let's
consider some of the abject failures
that led ultimately to a woefully
incomplete reconstruction. And I'll give
you two major examples. First, the rise
of sharecropping. So, it was generally
agreed that in order for the formerly
enslaved blacks of the South to thrive
socially and economically, they had to
own land. And as I mentioned earlier,
this idea was proven true in the
beginning of reconstruction when wartime
orders mandated that freed men be
granted land that formerly belonged to
Confederates. However, Andrew Johnson,
no friend of black people, rescended the
order and redistributed those lands back
to their former white owners, leaving
many black southerners destitute and
without hope of economic independence.
So, now with so many black southerners
without an acre of land to their name,
they needed some way to earn a living.
Well, as it happened, all the white
cotton planters needed laborers on
account of their enslaved workforce had
been forcefully taken from them. And
that's when we see the rise of a new
labor system in the south, namely
sharecropping. Under this system, black
farmers and quite a few poor white
farmers as well entered into a
contractual relationship with the
plantation owner. They would be given
tools and their own plot of land to farm
in exchange for a percentage of the
harvest due to the land owner. And you
know, while in theory this arrangement
seemed to contribute to black farmers
economic independence, in practice it
was simply race-based slavery by a
different name. You see, sharecroppers
had to buy household items on credit
while waiting for their harvest. And it
was the plantation owners selling the
farmers those goods. So bad harvests and
corrupt accounting practices meant that
many black sharecroers found themselves
deeply indebted to plantation owners and
were therefore bound to the land, living
by the strict rules enacted by the
planters. And if that smells a lot like
slavery to you, well, your sniffer is
working just fine. And this arrangement
persisted into the 20th century and
prevented generations of black families
from achieving economic independence and
building wealth that they could pass
down to their children. But then the
second category of failure during
reconstruction was the constant erosion
of black civil rights. And much of that
occurred as a result of Supreme Court
decisions. For example, in a series of
cases known as the slaughterhouse cases
and then later in United States v.
Crookshank, the court systematically
restricted the protection of civil
rights guaranteed in the 14th amendment.
The Crookshank case was the result of
violence against black people in
Louisiana during what became known as
the Kfax massacre. And long story short,
Louisiana's election for governor in
1872 was loaded with corruption and the
results were not surprisingly hotly
contested. And since the Democratic
candidate favored the imposition of
white supremacy laws in Louisiana, a
group of black Louisianans occupied the
town courthouse in order to protest
against such policies. And then a white
mob arrived made up of no small number
of the Ku Klux Clan. And then they
murdered somewhere between 60 and 150 of
the black men in the courthouse and then
throughout the surrounding neighborhood.
And so when this case came before the
Supreme Court, the judges ruled that the
14th amendment did not protect black
Americans from an attack against their
civil rights if the attackers were
private citizens, which is to say not
the federal or state government. And as
a result of this ruling, the Ku Klux
Clan, now immune from federal or state
prosecution, unleashed enormous amounts
of violence against southern blacks. So
yeah, by the end of reconstruction, the
postbellum south looked eerily similar
to the antibbellum south and could
already be considered a failure. But the
official end of reconstruction occurred
in 1877 as a result of a hotly contested
presidential election. So in the
presidential election of 1876, the
Democrat Samuel J. Tilden ran against
the Republican Rutherford B. Hayes. And
long story short, by all accounts,
Tilden probably should have won the
election. However, Congress was
responsible for certifying the election
and because 20 of the electoral votes
were contested, the rival factions could
not come to an agreement. So, they
struck a deal in what became known as
the compromise of 1877. And to be clear,
this wasn't an official written
agreement, but rather one made in
secret. And the deal went like this. The
Republican Rutherford be Hayes could
have the presidency in exchange for the
removal of federal troops from the
South. And look, in truth, there was
already plenty of support for ending the
federal occupation of the South, even by
northerners who had grown weary of the
constant focus on reconstruction and
really wanted to move on to other
things. And a big part of that weariness
came from the profound economic
suffering caused by the panic of 1873
and the reemergence of corruption in
party politics. Anyway, as federal
troops were removed from the South, most
of the Republicans went with them. And
that gave a whole slew of redeemer
Democrats the opportunity to rise to
power and shape southern society in
their own image. In fact, they styled
themselves as redeemers because their
goal was to cleanse the South of the
corrupting effects of racial equality
policies forced on them by the Northern
Republicans. And that is exactly what
happened. And the tragedy of
reconstruction's failure is going to
continue to haunt us in the next unit as
well. Well, okay, since we're at the end
of a unit, you might want to click here
to grab my A Bush Heimler review guide,
which is going to help you study as fast
as possible. I'm glad you came around
and I'll see you in unit 6. Himler out.